I was going to speak at a TED conference.
أنني بصدد الحديث على منصة مؤتمر TED
I ran across the hall to one of my classrooms
جريت عبر القاعة تجاه أحد الفصول التي أدرسها
to inform my students.
لأخبر طلابي.
"Guess what, guys?
"احزروا ماذا يا شباب؟
I've been asked to give a TED Talk."
طلب مني تقديم محادثة TED."
The reaction wasn't one I quite expected.
لم يكن رد فعلهم ما توقعته أبداً.
The whole room went silent.
حل الصمت على كل القاعة.
"A TED Talk? You mean, like the one you made us watch on grit?
سألني محمد: "محادثة TED؟ أتقصدين مثل التي جعلتنا نشاهدها على الرمل؟
Or the one with the scientist that did this really awesome thing with robots?"
أو تلك التي قدمها العالم الذي يفعل أشياء
Muhammad asked.
"نعم، بالضبط."
"But Coach, those people are really important and smart."
"ولكن أيتها المدربة، هؤلاء الأشخاص مهمون جداً وأذكياء."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I know that."
"أعرف ذلك."
"But Coach, why are you speaking? You hate public speaking."
"ولكن أيتها المدربة، لماذا سوف تتحدثين؟ أنت تكرهين الخطابة العامة."
"I do," I admitted,
أقررت بذلك: "نعم."
"But it's important that I speak about us, that I speak about your journeys,
"ولكن من الأهمية بمكان أن أتحدث عنا، عن رحلاتكم،
about my journey.
عن رحلتي أنا،
People need to know."
الناس بحاجة أن يعرفوا."
The students at the all-refugee school that I founded
قرر جميع الطلاب في مدرسة المهاجرين التي أسستها
decided to end with some words of encouragement.
أن ينهوا أسئلتهم ببعض كلمات التشجيع.
"Cool! It better be good, Coach."
"رائع! من الأفضل أن يكون جيداً."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There are 65.3 million people who have been forcibly displaced
يوجد 65.3 مليون شخص هُجروا قسراً
from their homes because of war or persecution.
من منازلهم بسبب الحرب والاضطهاد.
The largest number, 11 million, are from Syria.
العدد الأكبر وهو 11 مليون يأتي من سوريا.
33,952 people flee their homes daily.
33.952 شخص يهربون من منازلهم يومياً.
The vast majority remain in refugee camps,
الأغلبية العظمى منهم تبقى في معكسرات المهاجرين،
whose conditions cannot be defined as humane under anyone's definition.
والتي لا يمكن تعريفها كإنسانية بأي شكل من الأشكال.
We are participating in the degradation of humans.
نحن نشارك في انحطاط البشرية.
Never have we had numbers this high.
لم يحدث أن وجد هذا الرقم الهائل.
This is the highest number of refugees since World War II.
هذا هو أكبر رقم للمهاجرين منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية.
Now, let me tell you why this issue is so important to me.
الآن، اسمحوا لي أن أخبركم لماذا هذا الأمر مهم بالنسبة لي.
I am an Arab. I am an immigrant.
أنا عربية. أنا مهاجرة.
I am a Muslim.
أنا مسلمة.
I've also spent the last 12 years of my life working with refugees.
كما أني قضيت آخر 12 سنة من حياتي أعمل مع المهاجرين.
Oh -- and I'm also gay.
أوه -- كما أني مثلية الجنس.
It makes me really popular these days.
الشيء الذي يجعلني مشهورة هذه الأيام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I am the daughter of a refugee.
ولكني ابنة مهاجر.
My grandmother fled Syria in 1964 during the first Assad regime.
هربت جدتي من سوريا في العام 1964 إبان حكم الأسد الأول.
She was three months pregnant when she packed up a suitcase,
كانت حاملاً في شهرها الثالث عندما حزمت حقيبتها،
piled in her five children and drove to neighboring Jordan,
جمعت أطفالها الخمسة وذهبت إلى الأردن المجاورة،
not knowing what the future held for her and her family.
لا تدري ما يحمل المستقبل لها ولأسرتها.
My grandfather decided to stay, not believing it was that bad.
قرر جدي البقاء، معتقداً أن الوضع ليس بهذا السوء.
He followed her a month later, after his brothers were tortured
لحق بها بعد شهر، بعد أن تم تعذيب إخوته
and his factory was taken over by the government.
واستولت الحكومة على مصنعه.
They rebuilt their lives starting from scratch
بدأوا حياتهم من الصفر
and eventually became independently wealthy Jordanian citizens.
وفي آخر الأمر، أصبحوا مواطنين أردنيين أثرياء مستقلين بذاتهم.
I was born in Jordan 11 years later.
ولدت في الأردن بعدها ب 11 سنة.
It was really important to my grandmother for us to know our history
اهتمت جدتي جداً بأن نعرف تاريخنا
and our journey.
ورحلتنا.
I was eight years old when she took me to visit my first refugee camp.
كان عمري 8 سنوات عندما أخذتني كي أزور معسكر اللاجئين الأول لي.
I didn't understand why.
لم أعرف السبب حينها.
I didn't know why it was so important to her
لم أعرف لِمَ يهمها جداً
for us to go.
أن نذهب إلى هناك.
I remember walking into the camp holding her hand,
أتذكر ذهابي إلى المعكسر ممسكةً بيدها،
and her saying, "Go play with the kids,"
وهي تقول لي: "اذهبي والعبي مع الأطفال،"
while she visited with the women in the camp.
بينما كانت تزور النساء في المعسكر.
I didn't want to.
لم أرد فعل ذلك.
These kids weren't like me.
لم يكن أولئك الأطفال مثلي.
They were poor. They lived in a camp.
كانوا فقراء ويعيشون في معسكر.
I refused.
رفضت ذلك.
She knelt down beside me and firmly said, "Go.
جثت على ركبيتها بجانبي وقالت لي بحزم، "اذهبي.
And don't come back until you've played.
ولا تعودي حتى تلعبي معهم.
Don't ever think people are beneath you
لا تفكري أبداً أن الناس أقل منك درجة
or that you have nothing to learn from others."
أو أن الآخرين لا يملكون شيئاً لتتعلميه منهم."
I reluctantly went.
ذهبت على مضض.
I never wanted to disappoint my grandmother.
لم أرد أبداً أن أُحبط جدتي.
I returned a few hours later,
عدت بعدها بساعات قلائل،
having spent some time playing soccer with the kids in the camp.
بعد قضاء بعض الوقت ألعب الكرة مع الأطفال في المعسكر.
We walked out of the camp,
خرجنا بعدها من المعسكر،
and I was excitedly telling her what a great time I had
وكنت أشعر بالإثارة وأنا أخبرها عن الوقت الرائع الذي قضيته
and how fantastic the kids were.
وكم أن الأطفال كانوا رائعين.
"Haram!" I said in Arabic. "Poor them."
"حرام!" قلت بالعربية. "مساكين."
"Haram on us," she said, using the word's different meaning,
قالت: "حرام علينا،" مستخدمةً معنى مختلفاً للكلمة،
that we were sinning.
أي أننا نحن المذنبون.
"Don't feel sorry for them; believe in them."
"لا تشعري بالأسى عليهم؛ بل آمني بهم."
It wasn't until I left my country of origin for the United States
ما إن غادرت موطني الأصلي إلى الولايات المتحدة
that I realized the impact of her words.
حتى لاحظت تأثير كلماتها.
After my college graduation, I applied for and was granted political asylum,
بعد تخرجي من الكلية، حصلت على اللجوء السياسي بعد أن تقدمت بطلب له،
based on being a member of a social group.
باعتبار كوني أنتمي لمجموعة اجتماعية.
Some people may not realize this,
قد لا يلاحظ بعض الناس هذا الأمر،
but you can still get the death penalty in some countries for being gay.
ولكن في بعض البلدان قد يصدر في حقك حكم الإعدام كونك مثلي الجنس.
I had to give up my Jordanian citizenship.
توجب علي الاستغناء عن جنسيتي الأردنية.
That was the hardest decision I've ever had to make,
كان ذلك أصعب قرار اتخذته،
but I had no other choice.
ولكن لم يكن لدي خيار.
The point is,
الفكرة هي،
when you find yourself choosing between home and survival,
عندما يتوجب عليك الاختيار بين الوطن والنجاة،
the question "Where are you from?" becomes very loaded.
يصبح السؤال "من أين أنت؟" صعباً جداً.
A Syrian woman who I recently met at a refugee camp in Greece
مؤخراً، قابلت امرأة سورية في معسكر لللاجئين في اليونان
articulated it best,
والتي بينت الأمر بوضوح،
when she recalled the exact moment she realized she had to flee Aleppo.
عندما تذكرتْ نفس اللحظة حين توجب عليها الهرب من حلب.
"I looked out the window and there was nothing.
قالت: "نظرتُ عبر النافذة ولم يكن هناك شيء.
It was all rubble.
كان كل شيء عبارة عن أنقاض.
There were no stores, no streets, no schools. Everything was gone.
لم يكن هناك متاجر أو شوارع أو مدارس. ذهب كل شيء.
I had been in my apartment for months,
قضيت شهوراً في شقتي،
listening to bombs drop and watching people die.
أستمع إلى أصوات القنابل وأشاهد الناس تموت.
But I always thought it would get better,
ولكن دائماً ما كنت أفكر أن الأوضاع سوف تتحسن،
that no one could force me to leave,
أن لا أحد يستطيع إجباري على الرحيل،
no one could take my home away from me.
أن لا أحد يستطيع نزع بيتي مني.
And I don't know why it was that morning, but when I looked outside,
ولكن لا أعرف لماذا في ذاك الصباح بالتحديد عندما نظرت خارجاً،
I realized if I didn't leave, my three young children would die.
أدركت أنه إن لم أغادر، فقد يموت أطفالي الثلاثة.
And so we left.
لذلك غادرنا.
We left because we had to, not because we wanted to.
غادرنا لأنه توجب علينا وليس لأننا أردنا ذلك.
There was no choice," she said.
لم يكن هناك خيار."
It's kind of hard to believe that you belong
إن من الصعب نوعاً ما أن تؤمن أنك تنتمي إلى مكان ما
when you don't have a home,
حينما تجرد من الوطن،
when your country of origin rejects you because of fear or persecution,
عندما يرفضك وطنك الأصلي بسبب الخوف أو الاضطهاد،
or the city that you grew up in is completely destroyed.
أو أن المدينة التي ترعرعت فيها أصبحت محطمة بالكامل.
I didn't feel like I had a home.
لم أشعر وكأن لي وطناً.
I was no longer a Jordanian citizen,
لم أعد مواطنة أردنية،
but I wasn't American, either.
ولكن لم أكن أمريكية أيضاً.
I felt a kind of loneliness
شعرت بشيء من الوحدة
that is still hard to put into words today.
شعور يصعب التعبير عنه بالكلمات.
After college, I desperately needed to find a place to call home.
بعد الكلية، احتجت بشدة أن أجد مكاناً أدعوه الوطن.
I bounced around from state to state
تجولت من ولاية إلى أخرى
and eventually ended up in North Carolina.
وانتهى بي المطاف في شمال كارولاينا.
Kindhearted people who felt sorry for me
عرض علي أشخاص عطوفون والذين شعروا بالشفقة علي
offered to pay rent
دفع الإيجار
or buy me a meal or a suit for my new interview.
أو شراء وجبة أو بدلة لمقابلات العمل الجديدة.
It just made me feel more isolated and incapable.
الشيء الذي أشعرني بمزيد من العزلة وعدم القدرة.
It wasn't until I met Miss Sarah,
إلى أن قابلت الآنسة سارة،
a Southern Baptist who took me in at my lowest and gave me a job,
المعمدانية الجنوبية التي آوتني ووفرت لي عملاً،
that I started to believe in myself.
حينها بدأت أؤمن بنفسي.
Miss Sarah owned a diner in the mountains of North Carolina.
تملك الآنسة سارة مطعماً في جبال شمال كارولاينا.
I assumed, because of my privileged upbringing
ظننتُ أنه بسبب نشأتي المميزة
and my Seven Sister education,
وأخواتي السبعة المتعلمات،
that she would ask me to manage the restaurant.
أنها ستطلب مني أن أدير المطعم.
I was wrong.
لقد كنت مخطأة.
I started off washing dishes,
بدأتُ بغسل الصحون،
cleaning toilets and working the grill.
وتنظيف الحمامات وتشغيل الشواية.
I was humbled; I was shown the value of hard work.
كنت خانعة؛ تعرفت على قيمة العمل الشاق.
But most importantly, I felt valued and embraced.
ولكن الأهم من ذلك، شعرت بالقيمة والقبول.
I celebrated Christmas with her family,
احتفلت بعيد الميلاد مع عائلتها،
and she attempted to observe Ramadan with me.
كما أنها حاولت معي القيام بشعائر رمضان.
I remember being very nervous about coming out to her --
أتذكر أني كنت مرتبكة جداً حين اعترفت لها --
I sat on the couch next to her
جلست على الأريكة بجانبها
and I said, "Miss Sarah, you know that I'm gay."
وقلت لها: "آنسة سارة، أني مثلية الجنس."
Her response is one that I will never forget.
كانت إجابتها والتي لن أنساها أبداً.
"That's fine, honey. Just don't be a slut."
"لا بأس عزيزتي. فقط تجنبي أن تصبحي عاهرة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I eventually moved to Atlanta, still trying to find my home.
انتهى الأمر بأن رحلت إلى أتلانتا، محاولة إيجاد وطن لي.
My journey took a strange turn three years later,
اتخذت رحلتي مساراً غريباً بعد ثلاث سنوات،
after I met a group of refugee kids playing soccer outside.
عندما قابلت مجموعة من الأطفال اللاجئين يلعبون الكرة في الجوار.
I'd made a wrong turn into this apartment complex,
كان ذلك عندما ضللت الطريق لهذا المجمع السكني،
and I saw these kids outside playing soccer.
ورأيت هؤلاء الأطفال يلعبون الكرة،
They were playing barefoot with a raggedy soccer ball
كانوا يلعبون حفاة الأقدام بكرة بالية
and rocks set up as goals.
ومرمى مصنوع من الصخور.
I watched them for about an hour,
شاهدتهم لقرابة الساعة،
and after that I was smiling.
وكنت أبتسم حينها.
The boys reminded me of home.
ذكرني الأطفال بالوطن.
They reminded me of the way I grew up playing soccer
ذكروني بالطريقة التي نشأت بها ألعب كرة القدم
in the streets of Jordan, with my brothers and cousins.
في شوارع الأردن، مع إخوتي وأبناء أهلي.
I eventually joined their game.
شاركتهم اللعب في آخر المطاف.
They were a little skeptical about letting me join it,
كانوا متشككين بعض الشيء في السماح لي بأن ألعب معهم،
because according to them, girls don't know how to play.
فبالنسبة لهم، لا يعرف الفتيات كيف يلعبن.
But obviously I did.
ولكن من الواضح أني أعرف.
I asked them if they had ever played on a team.
سألتهم إن حدث ولعبوا في فريق من قبل.
They said they hadn't, but that they would love to.
قالوا أنهم لم يفعلوا ولكنهم يحبون ذلك.
I gradually won them over, and we formed our first team.
أقنعتهم بذلك تدريجياً، ومن ثَمَّ شكلنا أول فريق لنا.
This group of kids would give me a crash course in refugees, poverty
أعطتني هذه المجموعة من الأطفال درساً واضحاً عن اللاجئين والفقر
and humanity.
وعن الإنسانية.
Three brothers from Afghanistan -- Roohullah, Noorullah and Zabiullah --
ثلاثة أطفال من أفغانستان -- روح الله ونور الله وزبي الله --
played a major role in that.
لعبوا دوراً محورياً في ذلك.
I showed up late to practice one day to find the field completely deserted.
أتيت يوماً ما متأخرة للتمرين لأجد الملعب خالياً تماماً.
I was really worried.
كنت قلقة جداً حينها.
My team loved to practice.
يحب فريقي التمرن.
It wasn't like them to miss practice.
كان غريباً منهم عدم الحضور للتمرين.
I got out of my car, and two kids ran out from behind a dumpster,
خرجت من سيارتي، فهرع طفلان من وراء سلة قمامة،
waving their hands frantically.
ملوحين بأيديهما بذعر.
"Coach, Rooh got beat up. He got jumped.
"أيتها المدربة، لقد ضُرب روح الله. لقد هوجم.
There was blood everywhere."
كانت الدماء في كل مكان."
"What do you mean? What do you mean he got beat up?"
"ماذا تقصد؟ ماذا تعني بأنه تعرض للضرب؟"
"These bad kids came and beat him up, Coach.
"هناك أطفال سيئون أوسعوه ضرباً.
Everybody left. They were all scared."
غادر الجميع. كانوا خائفين جميعاً."
We hopped into my car and drove over to Rooh's apartment.
قفزنا إلى عربتي وقدنا تجاه شقة أهل روح.
I knocked on the door, and Noor opened it.
قرعت الباب ففتحه نور.
"Where's Rooh? I need to talk to him, see if he's OK."
"أين روح؟ أحتاج أن أتحدث إليه، هل هو بخير."
"He's in his room, Coach. He's refusing to come out."
"هو في غرفته أيتها المدربة. إنه يرفض الخروج."
I knocked on the door.
قرعت الباب.
"Rooh, come on out. I need to talk to you.
"روح، أخرج. أنا بحاجة إلى الحديث معك.
I need to see if you're OK or if we need to go to the hospital."
أحتاج أن أعرف إن كنت بخير أم نذهب إلى المستشفى."
He came out.
خرج من الغرفة.
He had a big gash on his head, a split lip,
كان لديه جرح كبير في رأسه، وشفة مشقوقة،
and he was physically shaken.
وكان جسده يرجف.
I was looking at him,
كنت أنظر إليه،
and I asked the boys to call for their mom,
ثم طلبت من الفتيان أن يُحضروا أمهم،
because I needed to go to the hospital with him.
لأنني أردت أخذه إلى المستشفى.
They called for their mom.
طلبوا من أمهم الحضور.
She came out.
جاءت.
I had my back turned to her, and she started screaming in Farsi.
كان ظهري مواجهاً لها، عندما بدأت تصرخ باللغة الفارسية.
The boys fell to the ground laughing.
سقط الأطفال على الأرض ضاحكين.
I was very confused,
كنت مرتبكةً للغاية،
because there was nothing funny about this.
لأنه لم يكن هناك شيء مضحك في الأمر.
They explained to me that she said,
وضحوا لي أنها قالت،
"You told me your coach was a Muslim and a woman."
"لقد قلتم لي أن مدربتكم مسلمة وأنها امرأة."
From behind, I didn't appear to be either to her.
من الخلف، لم أبدو أياً من ذلك بالنسبة لها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I am Muslim," I said, turning to her.
أدرت وجهي تجاهها وقلت لها: "أنا مسلمة".
"Ašhadu ʾan lā ʾilāha ʾilla (A)llāh,"
"أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله."
reciting the Muslim declaration of faith.
مرددةً الشهادتين.
Confused,
محتارةً،
and perhaps maybe a little bit reassured,
وربما مطمئنة بعض الشيء،
she realized that yes,
أدركتْ الأمر،
I, this American-acting, shorts-wearing, non-veiled woman,
أنا، من تتصرف كأمريكية وترتدي قميصاً وليست محجبة،
was indeed a Muslim.
كنت مسلمة بحق.
Their family had fled the Taliban.
هربت عائلتهم من حركة طالبان.
Hundreds of people in their village
قُتل المئات من الناس
were murdered.
في قريتهم.
Their father was taken in by the Taliban,
أخذت حركة طالبان والدهم،
only to return a few months later, a shell of the man he once was.
ولكنه عاد بعد بضعة أشهر هيكلاً لما كان من قبل.
The family escaped to Pakistan,
هربت العائلة إلى باكستان،
and the two older boys, age eight and 10 at the time,
وكان عمر الولدين الكبيرين 10 سنوات حينها،
wove rugs for 10 hours a day to provide for their family.
ينسجان السجاد ل10 ساعات في اليوم كي يساعدوا عائلتهم.
They were so excited when they found out that they had been approved
كانوا متحمسين للغاية حينما علموا أنه تم قبولهم
to resettle in the United States,
للذهاب للولايات المتحدة،
making them the lucky 0.1 percent who get to do that.
مما يجعلهم ضمن نسبة 0.1 في المئة الذين يحصلون على تلك الفرصة.
They had hit the jackpot.
فقد ربحوا الجائزة الكبرى.
Their story is not unique.
قصتهم ليست فريدة من نوعها.
Every refugee family I have worked with has had some version of this.
كل عائلة من المهاجرين من الذين عملت معهم لهم قصة شبيهة بهذه.
I work with kids
أعمل مع الأطفال
who have seen their mothers raped, their fathers' fingers sliced off.
الذين رأوا أمهاتهم يُغتصبن، وأصابع آبائهم تُقطع.
One kid saw a bullet put in his grandmother's head,
أحد الأطفال رأى رصاصة موضوعة في رأس جدته،
because she refused to let the rebels take him to be a child soldier.
لأنها رفضت السماح للمتمردين بأخذه ليكون جندياً.
Their journeys are haunting.
رحلاتهم مؤثرة.
But what I get to see every day is hope, resilience, determination,
ولكن ما أراه كل يوم هو الأمل والتصميم والعزم
a love of life
وحب الحياة
and appreciation for being able to rebuild their lives.
والتقدير لكونهم قادرين على إعادة بناء حياتهم من جديد.
I was at the boys' apartment one night,
كنت في شقة الأولاد ذات ليلة،
when the mom came home after cleaning 18 hotel rooms in one day.
عندما عادت الأم إلى المنزل بعد تنظيفها ل18 غرفة فندق في يوم واحد.
She sat down, and Noor rubbed her feet,
جلستْ أرضاً وقام نور بتدليك قدميها،
saying that he was going to take care of her once he graduated.
قائلاً أنه سيعتني بها حالما يتخرج.
She smiled from exhaustion.
ابتسمتْ من الإرهاق.
"God is good. Life is good. We are lucky to be here."
"الله طيب. الحياة طيبة. نحن محظوظون كوننا هنا."
In the last two years, we have seen an escalating anti-refugee sentiment.
خلال السنتين الماضيتين رأينا مشاعر متصاعدة ضد اللاجئين.
It's global.
الأمر عالمي.
The numbers continue to grow because we do nothing to prevent it
الأرقام تزداد لأننا لا نفعل شيئاً لمنع الأمر
and nothing to stop it.
أو لوقفه.
The issue shouldn't be stopping refugees from coming into our countries.
يجب أن لا يكون الحل منع اللاجئين من القدوم إلى بلداننا.
The issue should be not forcing them to leave their own.
يجب أن يكون الحل عدم إجبارهم على مغادرة بلدانهم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Sorry.
آسفة.
How much more suffering,
كم قدر المعاناة،
how much more suffering must we take?
كم قدر المعاناة التي يجب علينا تحملها؟
How many more people need to be forced out of their homes
كم عدد من يجب عليهم مغادرة بلدانهم قسراً
before we say, "Enough!"?
قبل أن نقول "كفى!"؟
A hundred million?
مئة مليون؟!
Not only do we shame, blame and reject them
ليس فقط أننا نعايرهم ونلومهم ونرفضهم
for atrocities that they had absolutely nothing to do with,
على الفظائع التي لا علاقة لهم بها،
we re-traumatize them,
ولكننا نصدمهم من جديد،
when we're supposed to be welcoming them into our countries.
بينما يفترض بنا أن نرحب بهم في بلداننا.
We strip them of their dignity and treat them like criminals.
نحن نجردهم من كرامتهم ونعاملهم كمجرمين.
I had a student in my office a couple of weeks ago.
كان هناك طالبة فى مكتبي قبل بضعة أسابيع.
She's originally from Iraq.
هي من العراق.
She broke down crying.
انفجرت بالبكاء.
"Why do they hate us?"
"لماذا يكرهوننا؟"
"Who hates you?"
"من يكرهك؟"
"Everyone; everyone hates us because we are refugees,
"الجميع؛ الجميع يكرهنا لأننا لاجئون،
because we are Muslim."
لأننا مسلمون."
In the past, I was able to reassure my students
في الماضي كنت قادرة على تطمين طلابي
that the majority of the world does not hate refugees.
أن الأغلبية العظمى من العالم لا يكره المهاجرين.
But this time I couldn't.
لكن هذه المرة لم أستطع.
I couldn't explain to her why someone tried to rip off her mother's hijab
لم أستطع أن أفسر لها لماذا حاول أحدهم نزع حجاب والدتها
when they were grocery shopping,
عندما كانوا يتسوقون في البقالة.
or why a player on an opposing team called her a terrorist
أو لماذا نادتها لاعبة في الفريق الخصم بالإرهابية
and told her to go back where she came from.
وأخبرتها أن تعود من حيث أتت.
I couldn't reassure her
لم أستطع تطمينها
that her father's ultimate life sacrifice
أن تضحية والدها العظيمة بحياته
by serving in the United States military as an interpreter
بالخدمة في الجيش الأمريكي كمترجم
would make her more valued as an American citizen.
ستجعل قيمتها أكبر كمواطنة أمريكية.
We take in so few refugees worldwide.
نحن نستوعب القليل جداً من اللاجئين حول العالم.
We resettle less than 0.1 percent.
ندمج أقل من 0.1 في المئة منهم.
That 0.1 percent benefits us more than them.
هذه النسبة تفيدنا أكثر مما تفيدهم.
It dumbfounds me how the word "refugee" is considered something to be dirty,
يُزعجني كيف أن كلمة "لاجئ" تُعتبر شيئاً قذراً.
something to be ashamed of.
شيئاً يُخجل منه.
They have nothing to be ashamed of.
ليس هناك ما يخجلون منه.
We have seen advances in every aspect of our lives --
لقد شهدنا تقدماً في مختلف مناحي حياتنا --
except our humanity.
ما عدا إنسانيتنا.
There are 65.3 million people who have been forced out of their homes
يوجد 65.3 مليون شخص أُجبروا على مغادرة أوطانهم
because of war --
بسبب الحرب --
the largest number in history.
أكبر رقم في التاريخ.
We are the ones who should be ashamed.
نحن من يجب أن نخجل من ذلك.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.